Okay הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba we take up our משנה Mishnah at
the bottom of כ"ו עמוד ב' Kaf Vav Amud Bet and we
have just done the important גמרא Gemara with lots of important גמרות
Gemaras about ספק חינוך safek chinuch and issues about also רבא Rava
specifically listing the different types of מצוות mitzvot and עבירות averot that
are possible in terms of one who does not take the אבידה
aveidah or takes it after יאוש yeush or takes it with the
intention of stealing it. We now pick up with the what do
you call it? We now pick up with the משנה Mishnah on
the bottom of כ"ו עמוד ב'. Kaf Vav Amud Bet. Let's take
a look. Just trying to find it. Okay fine.
So the משנה Mishnah says the following: מצא בחנות הרי אלו שלו.
matsa b'chanut harei elu shelo. If you find a מציאה metziah in
a store you can keep it and רש"י Rashi says this is
לא סימן lo siman because if there's a סימן siman I mean
that gets to the question if you might remember right about רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר. Rabi Shimon ben Elazar. Well מקום makom isn't a
סימן, siman, things keep on getting I mean you're not finding a
package of cereal on the shelves of the store that is not
what מצא בחנות matsa b'chanut means. You find some coin on the
floor of the floor, you find a מציאה. metziah. So the point
is is that it clearly מקום makom is not a סימן, siman,
things are getting kicked around and moved around. The question is is
that would סימן siman itself be good? That gets to the רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר Rabi Shimon ben Elazar question about מקום שהרבים מצויים
makom sheharabim metzuyim but רש"י Rashi maybe to avoid that whole discussion
just says that it's a thing without a סימן. siman. הרי אלו
שלו, harei elu shelo, you get to keep it. בין התיבה ולחנווני
bein hateivah v'lachnevani now also we take very much would be talking
about money here. So you find it between the box like the
what we call the counter, the where you put the and the
register, right, but the counter in front of the of the person
who works at the register but the counter in front of the
של חנווני shel chanvani that's of the storekeeper that money fell from
the storekeeper. Okay from the till. לפני שולחני הרי אלו שלו lifnei
shulchani harei elu shelo in front of the money changer then you
can keep it. You find loose coins on the floor in front
of the money changer. בין הכיסא ולשולחני bein hakiseh v'lashulchani between the
money changer and the chair that the money changer is in, you
know between the you know where the money changer sits and like
the table where the money is exchanged, it's presumed
then הרי אלו של שולחני harei elu shel shulchani then it dropped
from the money changer. הלוקח פירות מחברו או ששלח לו חברו פירות
halokeach peirot mechavero o sheshalach lo chavero peirot you purchased fruit or
you were sent a gift of fruit ומצא בהן מעות umatsa bahen
ma'ot and there was money in them. So הרי אלו שלו harei
elu shelo you can keep it, which is strange. Why? You assume
well I know definitely who it came from, it came from the
person who sold me the fruit.
So we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. אם היו צרורים
נוטל ומכריז im hayu tserurim notel umachriz if they were in a
little bundle so then you know the bundle the knot is a
סימן, siman, the number is a סימן, siman, then you have to
announce it. But the funny thing is here is that why don't
we just assume that it was accidental and it definitely came from
your friend and return it to your friend? Presumably there's no יאוש
yeush if he you know wasn't aware of it. It's יאוש שלא
מדעת. yeush shelo mada'at. Okay so we'll see about that in the
גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look at the first at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabi Elazar אפילו מונחים על גבי
שולחן afillu munachim al gabei shulchan when it says that you have
to you can keep it, it's even if it's on the table
as long as it's not directly between the table and the money
changer. Okay it's not.
תנן לפני שולחני הרי אלו שלו tnan lifnei shulchani harei elu shelo
if it's in front of the money changer it's yours. הא על
גבי שולחן ha al gabei shulchan so in front of the money
changer presumably means in front of the in front of the table
so the implication would be if on the table לשולחני lashulchani the
money changer gets to keep it. הא ha that's the רישא reisha
of the משנה. Mishnah. אימא סיפא eima seifa let's look at the
end of the משנה. Mishnah. בין הכיסא ולשולחני של שולחני bein hakiseh
v'lashulchani shel shulchani between the chair and the שולחני shulchani the שולחני
shulchani here presumably means the שולחן, shulchan, not the not the money
changer. So between the chair and the table בין הכיסא ולשולחני של
שולחני bein hakiseh v'lashulchani shel shulchani
it's close to the money changer. הא על גבי שולחן ha al
gabei shulchan it sounds like if it was on the table שלו
shelo you get to keep it.
So אלא ela so basically the whole משנה Mishnah avoided the question
about the table itself. It says if it's before the table you
get to keep it. If it's between the chair and the table
it's the money keepers. How about if it's on the table itself?
How about if it's on the
chair? אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה ela meha leka lemishma mina from
here you cannot infer. רבי
אלעזר Rabi Elazar so מהא מנא ליה? meha mana leh? So okay
so if it's not inferable from the משנה Mishnah what leads רבי
אלעזר Rabi Elazar to say that if it's on the table you
get to keep it? אמר רבא מתניתין קשיא ליה Amar Rava matnitin
kashya leh it's bothered by the משנה. Mishnah. מהי דקתני בין הכיסא
ולשולחני של שולחני mahi dektani bein hakiseh v'lashulchani shel shulchani
because why did it say between the chair and the table? ליתני
על השולחן linitni al hashulchan just say if it's on the table
it goes to the money changer then it would have been obvious
that if it's between the table and the chair it goes to
the money changer. וכי תימא מצא בשולחנות vechi teima matsa beshulchanot why
didn't it say if you found in the money changing area? Presumably
that's what שולחנות shulchanot means. כי דקתני רישא מצא בחנות kidektani reisha
matsa b'chanut the רישא reisha of the משנה Mishnah says found in
the store and then it talked about between the register and the
storekeeper. So here the parallel should have been you found in the
money changing area and then contrast it to between the money changer
and the table. שלו. shelo. So why did it say לפני השולחני?
lifnei hashulchani? אלא שמע מינה אפילו מונחים על גבי שולחן הרי אלו
שלו. ela shema mina afillu munachim al gabei shulchan harei elu shelo.
from
you anything in front of the money changer, including the table itself,
that is הרי אלו שלו. harei eilu shelo. Alright, not exactly clear
to me the דיוק diyuk because it seems to me sometimes the
word שלחני shulchani here means money changer and sometimes it means the
table. But anyway, we're reading the phrase לפני השלחני lifnei hashulchani meaning
anything in front of him. So in front of him includes the
table in front of him. Inside he sits at a table? No,
I mean by the table. He's here, the table is the counter,
he's here, the table is here, you come in front of the
table, you put your money down and they exchange money on the
table. Where does he keep his money? Somewhere behind the rest of
it. Well, yeah, yeah, basically, yeah he keeps his money behind the
table. Any money he takes off, he takes off the table and
puts somewhere behind the table. So between me and the table, obviously
it's for me, from the table that way is from the people
that are changing money. How about if it's money was loose money
was left on the table itself? Alright, so it could have fallen
from random people and then you can keep it or could fall
from me and then you have to give it back to me.
So anyway the דיוק diyuk is לפני השלחני lifnei hashulchani is read
as anything in front of me, which includes the table itself, you
assume came from random people. I don't know why we focus on
the שלחני shulchani case and not on the חנות chanut case. Also,
what if it's what if it's בין תיבה לחנוני? bein teva lachanzvani?
What if it's on the תיבה teva itself? Like what if it's
on the counter itself? Seems to me it's exact same question. Alright,
I don't know, anyway. Good question though. Would you care to comment
on
this is such a classic methodology,
the Talmudic methodology that you try you don't try to directly articulate
principles. Right, but you kind of infer a דיוק diyuk from the
text. Right, and like it would be it would make to us
it would make a lot more sense to say well, what makes
sense in that case? Right, but what the גמרא Gemara does get
to eventually but usually starts very much by the concrete. Look, I
mean it's true in the תורה Torah itself, in general the development
of law starts from concrete cases and then gets abstracted, right? The
תורה Torah says כי יגח שור את שור רעהו ומת ומכרו את
השור החי, ki yigach shor et shor reehu vamet umacharu et hashor
hachai, right? It all talks, it doesn't, it speaks very concretely
and then, so there I mean historians of or whatever academics have
definitely like done a study like you look that as the history
of the development continues, the abstract you focus more and more on
abstraction. Like you see a nice transition stage when you get to
a משנה Mishnah that says something like, it says in this case
this and this and this, in this case this, in this case
this, in this case this, זה הכלל, zeh haklal, כל ש- kol
she-
whatever is whatever and כל ש- kol she- is from me so
you started from concrete case law and then you gave the general
rule. זה הכלל, zeh haklal, right, tried to well that's what it
means, we start from concrete law and then we pull back and
we abstract. Now, by the way, it's always very helpful to have
both
because if you just do the abstraction you don't know exactly how
that translates. Right, that's true, yeah. Is the
חנות chanut private property? The חנות chanut is presumably it's like a
store in general and then why isn't the חנות chanut owner, meaning
like,
חצרו של אדם קונה לו, chatzeiro shel adam konah lo, so
this is an interesting question, gets to תוספות's Tosafot question yesterday about
why
can't there be a יד yad over there, there's no יד yad
over there.
It's an interesting question. It's an interesting question.
I mean it's אינה משתמרת, einah mishtameret, so that's certainly true. Right,
yeah. Wait, can't he lock up the store at the end of
the day? No, it's not משתמרת, mishtameret, no, it doesn't mean you
can't lock up at the end of the day, it means that
something that's there right now is I can't protect it from other
people from getting it. I mean in theory I can kick everybody
out of my store but I think a place that's essentially a
common
thoroughfare, a store that's open to everyone is not a מקום משתמר.
makom mishtamer. And so therefore it's not going to be קונה, koneh,
right. Although it would be קונה koneh if you're עומד בצד חצרו,
omed betzad chatzero, it's an interesting question. Alright let's take a look
at the end here at the next stage. הלוקח פירות מחברו. halokeiach
peirot mechavero. So if you buy fruit, so then it says that
you are, and then you keep the money in the fruit unless
it's like bound up and has a סימן, siman, which is funny,
you know who it came from. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
ריש לקיש משום רבי ינאי amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabbi Yannai לא
שנו
אלא בלוקח מן התגר, lo shanu ella balokeiach min hataggar, it's only
if you buy from a merchant, from the person who buys from
the wholesalers, and he's the one that sold you the fruit or
he's the one that gave it to you as a gift. אבל
בלוקח מבעל הבית, aval balokeiach mibaal habayit, if you take from the
actual farmer, from the guy who grew the fruit, חייב להחזיר, chayav
lehachazir, then you know it came from him and presumably he's not
מתיאש mityaeish because it's not a סימן siman because A: he doesn't
know it, so it's יאוש שלא מדעת, yeush shelo madaat, B: if
he does, he knows you probably have it so he'll ask you
for it. Okay, וכן תני תנא קמיה דרב נחמן vechein tani tanna
kamei deRav Nachman לא שנו אלא בלוקח מן התגר, lo shanu ella
balokeiach min hataggar, it's only if you bought from the merchant because
then he gets from a lot of different types of wholesalers. So
A, so תוספות Tosafot points out A... if it came from a
wholesaler or if it came from the merchant. But ב, Beis, even
if it came from definitely a wholesaler, you don't know which wholesaler
it came from and they're מיאש miyaesh as well because they figure,
at this stage the merchant's got it, so I'm never going to
get it back because it's mixed up with every- everybody else's, you
know, fruit that the merchant or grain or whatever that the merchant
buys. Okay, so once that happens it's סתם stam like finding a
מציאה metziah in the street. The loser doesn't expect that he can—the
person who lost doesn't expect he can find the person who has
it. אבל בלוקח מבעל הבית חייב להחזיר. Aval belokeach miba'al habayis chayav
lehachazir. אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman, כי בעל הבית
בעצמו דשן? ki ba'al habayis b'atzmo dashan? I don't get it, even
if you buy from the farmer, the farmer himself was not the
one who threshed it. Again, סתם פירות stam peiros here, it's not
the word we associate with פירות, peiros, but סתם פירות stam peiros
seems to be basically like grain. Okay, so even if it's the
owner, even if you buy from the farmer, you should still say
you're allowed to keep it because how do you know, maybe—obviously he
has a lot of workers, so some workers' money that fell in
and got mixed up into the grain and not necessarily the owner's.
So you know, why we should assume that there's יאוש yeush there
because they don't know, anybody who loses it will assume that the
person who finds it—the person who finds it there's no סימן, siman,
won't know who lost it, could have been any of the workers,
so won't have a legitimate claim of getting it back. And anyway
הגמרא hagmorah says מאי בינייהו? mai beinayhu?
And then it says, oh, well you know, what מאי בינייהו mai
beinayhu is how do you interpret this משנה. mishna. You know, so
sometimes you're right, I mean very often it's—it starts very concrete and
sometimes it doesn't get abstract. Yeah, isn't it private property?
חנות chanut is presumably, presumably like a store in general. I mean,
why isn't it like חנות chanut owner, meaning like, you know, חצר
שאינה משתמרת. chatzer she'eina mishtameres.
That's an interesting question, gets to תוספות'ס Tosafos's question yesterday. With רש"י
Rashi there was something that was very good though.
It's an interesting question. It's an interesting question.
I mean it's אינה משתמרת, eina mishtameres, so that's certainly true. Right,
yeah. Well he can he can he—it is משתמרת, mishtameres, can't he
lock up, doesn't he lock up? No, it's not—no, it doesn't mean
you can't lock up at the end of the day. It means
that something that's there right now is I can't protect it from
other people from getting it, I mean I could, I fear I
could kick everybody out of my store, but I think the point
is it's essentially a common thoroughfare, you know, store that's open to
everyone is not a מקום משתמר. makom mishtamer. And so therefore it's
not קונה. koneh. Right. Although it would be קונה koneh if you're
עומד בצד חצירו, omed betzad chatzeiro, it's an interesting question. All right,
let's take a look at the end here at the next stage.
והלוקח פירות מחברו. Vehalokeach peiros michaveiro. So if you buy fruit, so
then it says that you are—what do you call it? And then
you have to keep the money in the fruit unless it's like
ground up and has a סימן. siman. Which is funny, you know
who it came from, so the ריש Reish says אמר ריש לקיש
משום רבי ינאי, Amar Reish Lakish mishum Rabi Yanai, לא שנו אלא
בלוקח מן התגר, lo shanu ela belokeach min hatagar, it's only if
you buy from a, you know, from the merchant, from the person
who buys from the wholesalers, and he's the one that sold you
the fruit or he's the one that gave it to you as
a gift. אבל בלוקח מבעל הבית, Aval belokeach miba'al habayis, if you
take from the actual farmer, from the guy who grew the fruit,
חייב להחזיר. chayav lehachazir. Then you know it came from him and
presumably he's not מיאש miyaesh because it's not a סימן siman because
א Aleph doesn't know it, so יאוש שלא מדעת. yeush shelo mida'at.
ב Beis if he does, he knows you probably have it so
he'll ask you for it. אוקיי, וכן תנא תנא קמיה דרב נחמן,
Okay, vechein tana tana kamei deRav Nachman, לא שנו אלא בלוקח מן
הגרדי, lo shanu ela belokeach min hagardi, it's only if you bought
from the merchant because then he gets from a lot of different
types of wholesalers. So א, Aleph, to תוספות'ס Tosafos's point, א Aleph
you don't know if it came from a wholesaler or if it
came from the merchant. But ב, Beis, even if it came from
definitely a wholesaler, you don't know which wholesaler it came from and
they're מיאש miyaesh as well because they figure, you know, at this
stage the merchant's got it, so I'm never going to get it
back because it's mixed up with every- everybody else's, you know, fruit
that the merchant or grain or whatever that the merchant buys. Okay,
so once that happens it's סתם stam like finding a מציאה metziah
in the street. The loser doesn't expect that he can—the person who
lost doesn't expect he can find the person who has it. אבל
בלוקח מבעל הבית חייב להחזיר. Aval belokeach miba'al habayis chayav lehachazir. אמר
ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman, כי בעל הבית בעצמו דשן?
ki ba'al habayis b'atzmo dashan? I don't get it, even if you
buy from the farmer, the farmer himself was not the one who
threshed it. Again, סתם פירות stam peiros here, it's not the word
we associate with פירות, peiros, but סתם פירות stam peiros seems to
be basically like grain. Okay, so even if it's the owner, even
if you buy from the farmer, you should still say you're allowed
to keep it because how do you know, maybe—obviously he has a
lot of workers, so some workers' money that fell in and got
mixed up into the grain and not necessarily the owner's. So you
know, why we should assume that there's יאוש yeush there because they
don't know, you know, anybody who loses it will assume that the
person who finds it—the person who finds it there's no סימן, siman,
won't know who lost it, could have been any of the workers,
so won't have a legitimate claim of getting it back. So they're
מיאש, miyaesh, you get to keep it, it's a classic case of
not having a סימן. siman. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, אטמיאשי? atmiyashei?
Should I therefore like erase it, should I throw out this ברייתא
braisa because now you're saying it doesn't make sense to make this
distinction? אמר ליה לא, Amar lei lo, תתרצי מתניתין כגון שדשנה על
ידי עבדו ושפחתו הכנענית. titarchei matnisin kegon shedashana al yedei avdo veshifchato
hakenanit. No,
it would be a case where the person—the farmer's workers are all
basically his slaves and therefore any money would be his money. But
if actually he would be employing, you know, free workers, so then
even if you know it came from this person's farm, you wouldn't
know who lost it and therefore you would be allowed to keep
it. Which is interesting, you wouldn't say that you can definitely give
it to the farmer and the farmer will say I'll ask around,
I'll find out if anybody lost the money. Again, as soon as
there's no סימן siman and you don't know exactly who it was
who lost it, that's a case of הרי אלו שלו. harei elu
shelo. Okay, let's take a look at the end here at the
next stage. Now let's take a look at the next משנה. mishna.
Now we turn to a classic, what do you call it, we,
you know, like I said yesterday when we taught רבא'ס Rava's הלכה
halacha about what type of עבירות aveirot you transgress and so on,
or what מצוות mitzvot you transgress. That's like a, would've been a
good opening discussion of מציאה. metzia. This next משנה mishna also would've
been a good opening discussion. It gets us to the פסוקים psukim
and it tells us the basic idea of how we know these
concepts we've been dealing with all along, the concept of a סימן
siman and the concept of יאוש. yeiush. So let's take a look
at the משנה. mishna. אף השמלה הייתה בכלל. Af hasimla hayta baklal.
שמלה Simla was included in the general statement, okay? Because the פסוק
pasuk says, you know, כי תראה שור אחיך או את שיו נדחים
והתעלמת מהם השב תשיבם לאחיך, ki tireh shor achicha o et seyo
nidachim vehitalamta mehem hashev teshivem le'achicha, and then one of the פסוקים
psukim there says, וכן תעשה לחמורו וכן תעשה לשמלתו וכן תעשה לכל
אבידת אחיך אשר תאבד ממנו ומצאתה
לא תוכל להתעלם. vechein ta'aseh lachamoro vechein ta'aseh lesimlato vechein ta'aseh lechol
aveidat achicha asher tovad mimenu umetzata lo tuchal lehitalem.
You should do this for his, you know, ox and for his
sheep and for his garment, and anything he loses you cannot ignore,
you must return. So why doesn't it just say
this is what you should do for anything that he loses? Why
does it have to list, you know, ox and sheep and donkey
and garment? So all of those things we're going to learn a
different הלכה halacha from them. And so what are we going to
learn from the word שמלה simla garment? הייתה בכלל hayta baklal was
included in any lost חפץ. chefetz.
So למה יצאת, lama yatzat, why was it singled out, why was
it, you know,
made given as
a
concrete example? להקיש לה, lehakesh lah, to associate things with it.
ולומר לך, velomar lach, to
tell you,
מה שמלה מיוחדת שיש בה סימנים, ma simla meyuchadet sheyesh bah simanim,
a
classic cloak as opposed to, you know, a sheep or an ox—I
mean I guess if you brand them they have a סימן siman
but it assumes classic garments, especially before the period of mass production,
you know, you really could identify your garment and not only could
you identify it to its eye, it assumes that there were distinguishing
marks. I don't know why that's taken as the default, thank you,
but it could be assumed. So ויש לה תובעים veyesh lah tov'im
and also, it's not like a הפקר hefker thing, it's like somebody's
obviously going to go around asking for it and not give up
hope of getting it back. אף כל דבר שיש בו סימנים ויש
לו תובעים חייב להכריז. af kol davar sheyesh bo simanim veyesh lo
tov'im chayav lehachriz. So this tells you the basic parameters that we've
been discussing from the beginning, you know, that the תורה, Torah, you
read the פשט pshat of the תורה, Torah, the תורה Torah never
says that you're ever allowed to keep it. The תורה Torah says
you always have to return it. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara says
no, שמלה simla tells us there are limits to when you have
to return it. Now there's a difference between סימנים simanim and תובעים.
tov'im. תובעים tov'im basically means is the key point that the owner's
not been מיאש. mitya'esh. Somebody is still looking for it. Okay, now
you could say that that's a function of סימנים, simanim, right? You
know, if you think you can identify it and get it back,
you're still going to be looking for it. But סימנים simanim also
tells you another point. סימנים simanim also tells you the point about
how do I know to trust you that it's yours that I
can return it to you? Okay, so those are separate issues, right?
One issue is that you're only obligated to return it if the
owner hasn't given up hope, the יאוש yeiush principle. Okay, we've had
before cases where there's a סימן siman and I give up hope
because I looked and I looked and I can't find it or
it's מקום שהרבים מצויים makom sheharabim metzuyim or whatever. Okay, there are
cases, you know, when there's no סימן siman and I haven't given
up hope because you know, like the case we just said by
the fruit, if you know it's my money and it came from
me even if there's no סימן, siman, I'm still going to expect
that
you're going to know it's mine and give it back to me
or it's יאוש שלא מדעת. yeiush shelo mida'at. So the סימן siman
and the יאוש yeiush are often linked but they're not the same
thing. So this is saying a standard cloak, A, you can identify
it and therefore or relatedly, you're always going to be hoping to
get it back, so there's no יאוש. yeiush. So that tells us
those two principles. Number one is you only keep an אבידה... aveida...
you have to return an אבידה aveida as long as the owner
is looking. for it, but you can keep it if there is
יאוש. yeush. And B, that a סימן siman is relevant. It's relevant
A because it usually impacts whether or not there will be יאוש,
yeush, and B it's relevant because even though I have no doubt
that the owner has not given up hope looking for this, how
do I know to trust you that you're the owner? How do
I know a סימן siman is good enough evidence to return it
to you? Okay, so those are the two important things and we'll
see how much both of those is really what we're learning from
the פסוק. pasuk. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
A question? Is this the first משנה Mishnah where we actually have
a talk about סימנים? simanim? Yes. I mean, the previous משניות Mishnayot
all assumed it, but it's a good point. Is it the first
משנה Mishnah that uses the word סימן? siman? I'm still, no you're
right. Speaking about what Dov mentioned and the whole abstraction
idea. The גמרא's Gemara been talking about סימנים simanim from the very
beginning, but until now we've just been giving concrete cases of סימנים.
simanim. We haven't abstracted it. And also the very משנה Mishnah is
also abstracting from the פסוק, pasuk, from the concrete case of שמלה
simlah to talking about the principles we learn from it. Okay, מאי
דכלל כל אלו? mai de-khlal kol elu? What does it mean a
שמלה simlah was already included in the general idea? אמר רבא: Amar
Rava: בכלל כל אבידת
אחיך, be-khlal kol aveidat achikha, any lost object. So why was this
singled out? אמר רבא: Amar Rava: למה לי דכתב רחמנא שור חמור
שה ושלמה? lama li de-khtav Rachmana shor chamor seh u-salmah? Why by
אבידה aveidah does it give all these examples of an ox, a
donkey, a sheep, and a garment? צריכי, tzrikhi, we need all of
them. Why not just say כל אבידת אחיך? kol aveidat achikha? If
it only said שמלה, simlah, a garment, הני מילי בעדים דגופא וסימנים
דגופא. hani milei be-edim de-gufa ve-simanim de-gufa.
That's only if you either bring witnesses that identify it as yours
or סימנים. simanim. Now the reason the גמרא Gemara is hedging its
bets is because,
not to ruin the surprise, but we're going to get up to
a discussion we've seen before whether סימנים דאורייתא. simanim de-Oraita. Whether
although the משנה Mishnah mentions סימנים, simanim, maybe that's only דרבנן. de-Rabbanan.
Maybe the real point of שמלה simlah is to tell you the
issue of יאוש. yeush. And maybe at a תורה Torah level, the
only way you can return an object to somebody is if that
person brings witnesses that testify, 'We recognize that,' no סימן. siman. But
a סימן siman is something you can describe, you know, whatever, 'Yeah,
it's got a black dot somewhere.' But the face, they know. We
directly see that and we can identify it, תפיסת עין, tfisat ayin,
that this belongs to שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so that's the question. Maybe
at the תורה Torah level you only return an object if there
are absolutely objective third-party witnesses who can identify with a תפיסת עין
tfisat ayin that this belongs to this person. So the גמרא Gemara
is going to hedge its bets as it discusses this, whether we're
talking about סימנים simanim or whether we're talking about עדים. edim. We'll
get back to this directly to the question of whether סימנים דאורייתא.
simanim de-Oraita. So if it had just said שמלה, simlah, I would
have said that that's only הני מילי בעדים דגופא וסימנים דגופא. hani
milei be-edim de-gufa ve-simanim de-gufa. Only if the way to identify it
is directly on something about the object itself. Either witnesses recognize the
object or, assuming סימנים simanim are good enough, that you have a
סימן siman on the object itself. אבל בחמור, aval be-chamor, but if
you have a donkey and let's say you don't have any identifying
marks on the donkey, you don't recognize the donkey. What you recognize
is the saddle. Okay, אבל בחמור בעדים דאוכף וסימנים דאוכף, aval be-chamor
be-edim de-ukaf ve-simanim de-ukaf, if I just have witnesses about the saddle
or a סימן siman on the saddle, אימא לא מהדרינן ליה, eima
lo mahadrinan leih, maybe don't return it, because maybe, you know, it's
my saddle on somebody else's donkey. כתב רחמנא חמור, ktav Rachmana chamor,
gave the example of a donkey, that you can assume it's
the same donkey, you know,
the saddle is not on a different donkey. We don't, but that's
what we do from the extra פסוק. pasuk. Okay, דאפילו חמור בסימני
האוכף, de-afilu chamor be-simanei ha-ukaf,
you can even return a donkey with סימנים simanim on the saddle.
שור ושה כתב רחמנא למה לי? shor ve-seh ktav Rachmana lama li?
Why the שור shor and שה? seh? שור דאפילו לגיזת זנבו וכל
שכן שה לגיזותיה. shor de-afilu le-gizat zanavo ve-khol she-ken seh le-gizoteiha. That
when you return the object, what about by-products that come off of
the object? How much are you responsible for them as well? So
if you find somebody's ox and then the tail sheds, you are
responsible to keep the shedding of the tail that that can be
used as some type of hair and that has some value and
you have to hold on to that and return it. And certainly
a sheep, you would have to, if it came time to be
sheared, you would have to shear it and hold on to the
shearings and return it. So it's not that they're parallel to the
אוכף. ukaf. In other words, the guy lost the animal but I've
only got the hair and that can be used to identify. No,
because before you used the word סימנים simanim and עדים edim and
here it's no. לכתוב רחמנא שור דאפילו לגיזת זנבו וכל שכן שה
לגיזותיו. likhtov Rachmana shor de-afilu le-gizat zanavo ve-khol she-ken seh le-gizotav.
So then just tell me an ox. If you have to return
even like the shedding of the tail, then certainly you would have
to return the wool of the sheep. אלא אמר רבא: ella amar
Rava: you know what, you're right. You didn't really need it to
say sheep, you could've figured that out from ox. אלא אמר רבא
חמור דבור לרבי יהודה ושה דאבידה דברי הכל. ella amar Rava chamor
de-vor le-Rabbi Yehuda ve-seh de-aveidah divrei ha-kol. קשיא, kashya,
you might remember this. Right, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that the
normal דרשה drasha by the pit in בבא קמא Bava Kamma is
ונפל שמה שור או חמור. ve-nafal shamma shor o chamor.
So one of the things we learn from חמור chamor is חמור
ולא כלים, chamor ve-lo kelim, that you're not liable if vessels get
broken or damaged in a pit. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
you are. So the גמרא Gemara says we don't head what he
does with the word donkey. why do what's the word donkey coming
to exclude for רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? so we don't know what
to do with the word donkey for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda by
the pit at the case of the pit. and the word שה
seh by lost objects we also don't know what to do because
we've already covered anything we needed to say we've said already. we've
discussed the issue about סימנים simanim by the by the garment and
יאוש. yeush. we've discussed the issue of of of a saddle that
we don't have to be afraid it's a different donkey and we
discussed the issue about the shearings. okay so we don't know what
you need the word שה seh for. okay so the גמרא Gemara
says ואימא לגללים הוא דאתא. ve-eima le-glalim hu de-ata. wait, i have
something you can tell me. this the same way the אחת achat
is coming to tell me you have to return even the sheddings
of the tail, maybe sheep is coming to tell me that you
have to return the dung. you find an animal and it you
know and it and it has its dung. now it doesn't mean
you necessarily have to hold on to it but maybe i don't
know sell it and you know give the guy the money for
it. it's good as fertilizer. so that's something that came from his
object, maybe you're responsible to return that as well. so the גמרא
Gemara says no גללים אפקורי מפקיר להו. glalim afkurei mafkir lehu. so
this is very interesting because this of course shows you what should
be pretty obvious especially when you know when the פסוקים pesukim are
so vague is that we use our own סברא sevara to decide
what we are or are not going to learn out from the
פסוקים. pesukim. so yes we do have an extra word. could we
say it means you have to return the dung? sure we could
say it but we're saying logically that's not going that's that doesn't
make sense to demand that. because you know if i lost my
sheep i only want my sheep back. i don't want i'm not
expecting you to if you're going to handle take care of my
sheep you can keep the you know the dung. that's not something
i'm going to want back. so because we assume people are מקפיד
makpid also you have to wonder if i'm paying for feeding the
sheep then the dung is a sort of byproduct of that but
we'll see later you can get from me reimbursement for your costs.
so maybe if i am reimbursing you for your costs you should
have sold the dung and given me that for money. so the
גמרא Gemara somehow assumes that people are מפקיר mafkir and you can't
say that that's included in the obligation. yes. is the use of
the word רחמנא Rachmana or רחמנא Rachmana an indication that this is
technically the תורה'ס Torah's view of
things? why no no רחמנא Rachmana just is the גמרא'ס Gemara's way
of talking about the תורה. Torah. oh God is רחמנא Rachmana yeah
always when it talks about the תורה Torah it says רחמנא Rachmana
the compassionate one but that's like a standard way of the גמרא
Gemara referring to it. okay גללים אפקורי מפקיר. glalim afkurei mafkir. ודילמא
לסימנים הוא דאתא. ve-dilma le-simanin hu de-ata. ah
but
maybe the extra word is coming to tell me that that because
what i've already hinted told you that there's a question whether סימנים
דאורייתא simanim d'oraita whether from a תורה Torah perspective you need עדים.
edim. so maybe the extra word sheep is coming to tell me
that even סימנים simanim are good enough so that's what the extra
word is. איבעיא להו iba'ya lehu because we have this question סימנים
דאורייתא דרבנן. simanim d'oraita d'rabbanan. the fact that you can trust somebody
again that's distinct from the issue that you need יאוש. yeush. okay
whatever the circumstances are that lead a person to be מיאש meya'esh
might sometimes be related to סימנים simanim might sometimes be related to
other things. יאוש yeush clearly you need but how do you know
the basis for returning something? is that based on סימנים simanim or
does the person need עדים? edim? that's our question. סימנים דאורייתא דרבנן
simanim d'oraita d'rabbanan so we don't know that. so therefore כתב רחמנא
שה katav Rachmana seh it's coming to tell me another thing דאפילו
בסימנים מהדרינן de-afillu be-simanin mahadrinan to tell me that you could there's
another type of object you could return even just by
סימנים. simanim. okay וסימנים דאורייתא ve-simanin d'oraita and it will teach me
that סימנים simanim is a דאורייתא d'oraita basis for returning an object.
אמרי לא amri lo הא דתניא ותנא לסימנים גבי שמלה ha detanya
u-tana lesimanin gabi simla
since in our it almost rhymes סימנים simanim and שמלה. simla. since
in our משנה Mishna it says שמלה simla teaches you both יאוש
yeush and
סימנים. simanim. so we're going to ask whether the משנה Mishna is
דוקא davka or לאו דוקא lav davka about the סימנים. simanim. but
clearly one way or another from our משנה Mishna it's clear that
we're not learning סימנים simanim from שה. seh. okay דתני מה שמלה
מיוחדת שיש בה סימנים ויש בה תובעים חייב להכריז אף כל דבר
שיש בו סימנים ויש בו תובעים חייב להכריז. de-tani ma simla meyuechedet
she-yesh bah simanim ve-yesh bah tov'im chayav le-hachriz af kol davar she-yesh
bo simanim ve-yesh bo tov'im chayav le-hachriz. so since our משנה Mishna
talks about סימנים simanim in the context of שמלה simla we're going
to ask is that a דאורייתא דרשה d'oraita drasha or not a
דאורייתא דרשה? d'oraita drasha? but it's clear that the author of our
משנה Mishna שמע מינה דשה לאו לסימנים הוא דאתא shema mina de-seh
lav le-simanin hu de-ata does not believe סימנים simanim is based on
the idea of שה. seh. so רש״י Rashi says that the point
there is that we therefore know that the author of our משנה
Mishna must learn something else out from שה seh right? because you
know if you're asking abstractly oh we got extra word that should
be a basis of סימנים דאורייתא simanim d'oraita but somehow we're saying
no no like whatever we're not doing the דרשות. drashot. the דרשות
drashot were done generations before. we're just trying to figure out what
the דרשות drashot were. okay so it's clear that the author of
our משנה Mishna does not learn סימנים simanim from שה seh because
the author is learning סימנים simanim from שמלה. simla. either he means
it or he doesn't mean it but that's where he's learning it
from. okay so שה seh must be some other דרשה drasha we
just don't know what it is. so at this moment though in
the סוגיא sugya סימנים simanim are דאורייתא d'oraita learned from שמלה. simla.
no the משנה Mishna says that סימנים simanim are the משנה Mishna
says that סימנים simanim are דאורייתא d'oraita learned from שמלה simla but
we're about to question yes that's the פשט pshat of the משנה
Mishna we're about to question if the משנה Mishna really means it
or not. okay so let's take a look. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan
אשר תאבד asher taveid but before we get to that we're going
to do another figuring out what
the פסוק pasuk means אשר תאבד ממנו ומצאתה asher taveid mimenu u-matzata
אשר תאבד. asher taveid. It's something worth losing, something of some substance,
I don't know. Okay,
so anyway that relates to the issue yesterday, remember we talked about
three people losing something that didn't have a שווה פרוטה shaveh prutah
to every individual? Anyway, רבי יהודה
אומר ומצאתה. Rabbi Yehuda omer u-matzata. No, you have to find it;
it has to be something worth finding. פרט לאבידה שאין בו שווה
פרוטה, p'rat l'aveida she-ein bo shaveh prutah, to exclude if it's not
something even worth finding, less than a פרוטה, prutah, you don't have
an obligation. So מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What difference does it make?
They're both saying the same idea: you don't have an obligation to
return it if it's less than a
פרוטה. prutah. אמר אביי משמעותא דקראי איכא בינייהו. amar Abaye mashmauta d'krai
ika beinaihu. Yeah, there is no practical difference between them, it's just
which part of the פסוק pasuk they want to learn it out
from. מר נפקא ליה מאשר תאבד, mar nafka lei m'asher tovad, one
learns it out from the word אשר תאבד, asher tovad, ומר נפקא
ליה מומצאתה, u-mar nafka lei m'u-matzata, and one learns it from the
word ומצאתה. u-matzata. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay fine, there's no
practical difference as to that דרשה, drasha, but based on which פסוק
pasuk you learn it, it prevents you from learning other things from
those words. ולמאן דנפקא ליה מאשר תאבד, u-l'man d'nafka lei m'asher tovad,
that you lost it, האי ומצאתה מאי עביד ליה? hai u-matzata mai
avid lei? What does he learn from the word
ומצאתה? u-matzata? הוא מיבעי ליה לכדרבנאי. hu mibaya lei l'che-d'Ravnai. This goes
back to the very beginning of our מסכת masechet at בבא קמא.
Bava Kamma. דאמר רבנאי, d'amar Ravnai, ומצאתה דאתא לידיה משמע. u-matzata d'ata
l'yadei mashma. He says that you're only obligated to return the lost
אבידה aveida of a Jew, אבידת אחיך. aveidat achicha. Okay, and then
the גמרא's Gemara question is, well maybe that means that you're not
obligated to pick up the lost object of a non-Jew, but maybe
after you picked it up you're obligated to return it. So רבנאי
Ravnai says no, it says לכל אבידת אחיך אשר תאבד ממנו ומצאתה.
l'chol aveidat achicha asher tovad mimennu u-matzata. And ומצאתה u-matzata means you've
already picked it up. So even after you've already picked it up,
your obligation is only to אחיך achicha and not to somebody who's
not אחיך. achicha. Okay, ומצאתה דאתא לידיה משמע. u-matzata d'ata l'yadei mashma.
And that's what we learn from ומצאתה u-matzata to exclude the case
of a non-Jew. ולמאן דנפקא ליה ומצאתה, u-l'man d'nafka lei u-matzata, so
the one that learns from ומצאתה u-matzata that it has to have
a פרוטה, prutah, האי אשר תאבד מאי עביד ליה? hai asher tovad
mai avid lei? What does he do with the words אשר תאבד?
asher tovad? מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יוחנן. mibaya lei l'che-d'Rabbi Yochanan. דאמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehotzadak, another thing we've learned before, מניין לאבידה ששטפה נהר שהיא
מותרת? minayin l'aveida she-shatafah nahar she-hi muteret? How do you know if
it's swept away by a river it's permissible even if the owner
is not
מייאש? miyamesh? שנאמר she-ne'emar לכל אבידת אחיך אשר תאבד ממנו, l'chol aveidat
achicha asher tovad mimennu, נאבד ממנו ומצוי לכל אדם, ne'evad mimennu u-matzui
l'chol adam, something that's lost from him but it's accessible to other
people, יצאה זו שאבודה הימנו ואינה מצויה לכל אדם. yatza'ah zu she-avudah
heimennu v'einah metzuyah l'chol adam. It excludes this case where it's lost
from him and from everybody else; that is not an אבידה aveida
that you're obligated to return. Okay, so we learn different things from
תאבד ממנו. tovad mimennu. We learn different things from ממנו; mimennu; it's
not really ומצאתה. u-matzata. Well, that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to
say. ומצאתה u-matzata tells you this idea of אתא לידיה, ata l'yadei,
and אשר תאבד ממנו asher tovad mimennu tells you this idea of
אבידה ששטפה נהר. aveida she-shatafah nahar. So now we're going to say,
but if you're using that פסוק pasuk to say your דרשה drasha
שווה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, where do you learn the other idea from?
ואידך האי דרבנאי מנא ליה? v'idach hai d'Ravnai m'na lei? So if
you learn that
ומצאתה u-matzata is coming to tell you שווה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, where
do you learn the idea of רבנאי Ravnai that even after you've
picked it up you don't have to return to a non-Jew? נפקא
ליה מומצאתה, nafka lei m'u-matzata, the extra
ו. vav. Fine. ואידך האי דרבי יוחנן מנא ליה? v'idach hai d'Rabbi
Yochanan m'na lei? רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan teaching of אבידה ששטפה נהר,
aveida she-shatafah nahar, where does he learn it from אשר תאבד ממנו?
asher tovad mimennu? If you learn from אשר תאבד asher tovad to
tell you שווה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, where do you learn that idea?
So the גמרא Gemara says נפקא ליה מממנו, nafka lei m'mimennu, as
Michael said. Okay, אשר תאבד asher tovad tells you שווה פרוטה, shaveh
prutah, and ממנו mimennu means you're the only one who lost it,
but it's accessible to other people. ואידך ממנו לא משמע ליה, v'idach
mimennu lo mashma lei, the other one doesn't make a דרשה drasha
based on ממנו. mimennu. Fine. Anyway, that's the idea that they're just
differing on which word to learn it out from and then it
forces you to learn other things out from different parts of the
words or from different words. רבא אמר, Rava amar, no, there actually
is a difference whether you learn it out from...